NATHANIEL TAGG

Westerville, OH | 614.602.7287 | nathaniel.tagg@gmail.com

DATA SCIENTIST AND PHYSICIST

Programming | Statistics | Mathematics | Data Analysis

- → Co-recipient of 2016 Breakthrough Prize in Fundamental Physics
 - → >100 scientific papers published in peer-reviewed journals
 - → https://github.com/nathanieltagg

SKILLS

Technical: Data visualization via web-based and 3d technologies, UNIX systems and sysadmin, web technology (full stack), data acquisition, data monitoring, Git/Subversion/CVS, Google/Azure APIs. AWS. SSH. Grid computing. ROOT. Database access and table design (MySQL, Postgres, SQLite, MongoDB), parallel processing. Expert with Monte-Carlo simulations. **Hardware:** Expert on photomultiplier and related optical sensors, scintillators, liquid argon time projection chambers, radiation counters, basic analog/digital circuits, and microprocessors.

Programming: Expert in C/C++, JavaScript, HTML/CSS, Python, Perl, bash, FORTRAN.

Scientific: Particle physics. Understanding of statistics and data analysis of large data sets (particularly multivariate fits and uncertainty estimation), detector calibration, data reconstruction, blind analysis techniques, successful grant writing, and technical writing.

Interpersonal: Years of experience mentoring, teaching, advising, collaborating long-distance, and leading groups within large multinational scientific collaborations.

CAREER SUMMARY

Professor of Physics, OTTERBEIN UNIVERSITY, Westerville, OH

2008-2021

Roles: Professor, 2019-March 2021; Associate Prof., 2013-2019; Dept. Chair, 2014-2018; Assistant Prof. 2008-2013

Key responsibilities: Completed all teaching and mentoring duties associated with being a full-time tenured professor while also carrying out an ambitious research agenda that involved collaborating with hundreds of scientists remotely.

Key personal accomplishments:

- Earned promotion to full professor 2 years early; earned tenure 2 years early.
- Secured continuous funding from the National Science Foundation, with each of my 4 grants being successful
 on their first application. This funding supported myself and my students.
- Concurrently served as Department Chair for 4 years. Handled issues external to the department, managed the departmental budget, planned course schedules, and overhauled the curriculum.
- Wrote educational software to facilitate rapid-feedback assessment and grade distribution.
- Built a web application that allowed for easy navigation of course and student-level academic data. Widely
 lauded as an important tool by administrators and faculty; enabled students to share their preferred pronouns
 and name pronunciations.

Key research accomplishments (most involving collaborations with 100+ scientists and training undergraduate students):

- Identified issues and needs for quality data-taking; took the initiative to rapidly create solutions
- Constructed tools for data extraction and organization that ensured reliable data operations with large detectors taking physics data
- Web-based data visualization tools: offered fast and intuitive access to data and simulations, used by researchers and for outreach/education.

PRIOR SCIENTIFIC EXPERIENCE

Visiting Scientist, TUFTS UNIVERSITY, Middlesex County, MA, 2005-2008

■ Led and coordinated the Calibration Group for the MINOS experiment, consisting of ~10 postdocs and grad students. Wrote the software platform to incorporate 8 different data studies into the same framework.

Research Assistant, BROOKHAVEN NATIONAL LABORATORY, Upton, NY, 2006-2008

- Contributed to early design conversations for the <u>Daya Bay experiment</u> and adapted database software. Postdoctoral Research Assistant, OXFORD UNIVERSITY, Oxford, UK, 2001-2005
 - Helped construct and integrate systems on the international MINOS experiment, and published results.

EDUCATION AND PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Ph.D. Physics, UNIVERSITY OF GUELPH, Ontario, Canada, 2001

• Completed a thesis on the Sudbury Neutrino Observatory, an experiment that won the 2015 Nobel Prize. M.Sc., Physics, UNIVERSITY OF GUELPH, 1996

B.Sc., Physics, UNIVERSITY OF LETHBRIDGE, Alberta, Canada, 1993

"Machine Learning" (course via Coursera.org), STANFORD UNIVERSITY, 2021

SELECTED PROJECTS (solo developer or team lead)

Construction Database Application (2020-2021): Authored a web application and RESTful interface for storing data related to DUNE experiment construction, including QA, QC, inventory, component relationships, checklists, and work instructions. Impact: Team adopted my solution rather than invest in \$70K work instruction software.

Online Monitoring Tool (2013-present): Authored a system to continuously sample and monitor from the MicroBooNE detector data stream, providing immediate interactive graphic display of high-volume data. Impact: Sole on-call support for this system, which has had > 99% uptime 24/7 for more than five years. Single inventor of a system that normally a team would develop.

Physics simulations for education (2013-2021): Wrote several JavaScript-based websites for teaching various physics properties including a dynamic, responsive system for diagramming electric field lines in 2D, an animated display of fields in an electromagnetic wave, a simulation of linear polarizers, and a full 2D wave simulation by differential equations that runs via WebGL on the client GPU. Impact: Tools are widely used for teaching

WebGL Event Display Visualization for Imaging Detectors (2013-2019): Authored a web application for visualizing neutrino data from high-resolution liquid argon time projection chambers. Impact: Nonexpert users could display events from live data streams or stored files with latencies orders of magnitude faster than any other system. The app is used for data monitoring, education, outreach, and reconstruction evaluation.

Run conditions catalog (2013): Developed Python application that monitored detector and beam systems to catalog all runs and interfaced with multiple database systems to provide useful summary data on run conditions, beam exposure, running time. Impact: Tool is vitally important to the operation of the experiment, making a very complex set of tasks much easier and allowing analyzers and operators convenient ways to identify and locate good data sets.

Web-based Event Visualization (2008-2013): Authored script-based web application that used a C++backend to serve data from the distributed storage system to a browser-based event viewer, allowing users to see live or reconstructed data from the MINERvA experiment. **Impact**: Allowed difficult analyses to be done easily and was used to create every event image ever published by the experiment. Tool still in heavy use by outreach groups.

TAKEAWAY

Comfortable working with teams and in large collaborations, I use software to simulate, calibrate, control, and acquire data from hardware (such as massive, complex particle detectors). I am expert with data analysis, data acquisition, databases, and visualization. I have created everything from hardware interfaces to web applications, both close-to-the-metal resource-intense computing and high-level GUIs. Adept at mastering new systems and technologies, I learn quickly, am an expert teacher and presenter, and excel at engaging all kinds of audience